so most people who practice the DH
today will'll do so as householders and
not as
monastics um but what people may not
necessarily realize is that to be a
householder today
um is probably quite different than
being a householder back in the Buddha's
day so I thought we could
explore some of the unquestioned views
and assumptions and blind spots because
people might think that they are in the
same position to approach and practice
dhama as householders back in the day
but actually there might be a lot of
additional dust uh um taking place
nowadays that people might not be fully
aware of so I thought we could go into
it and see was
involved so that will
be one of the main differences that
would stand out in terms of how people
generally live their lives now compared
to back in India when the Buddha was
alive well certainly the level of
comfort in these days it's a we leave a
little bit like uh kings and
queens uh the degree of uh safety
security much higher in terms of comfort
how we
leave I would see that the you know with
hold the health care for example or
um
food we can rely on the food which
is
available it's more kind of predictable
more kind
of secure say life so less exposure to
the kind of uncertainty and uh the
changes which involve in in natural
process of Life
uhhuh yeah so some developments right
better hygiene standards Healthcare
things like this um that's definitely
progress and there is a widespread idea
actually we should question this idea of
progress because it's a fatal mistake to
conflate the outer technological level
where there has been progress down the
ages but if people don't put put that on
the right level and think that because
they have been born in the 20th or 21st
century that they are there for
necessarily better humans than back in
the day right when you take the progress
on the inner existential level then
that's already a sort of a conceited um
arrogant take on things that will become
an obstacle if you actually want to
practice Dharma so yeah there is that
progress and that progress outwardly
technologically is not actually a
problem but you also mentioned the level
of comfort
and that might actually be an obstacle
in the context of practicing dhama in
fact that's even this where the Buddha
is praising the leavis for using wooden
blocks as
pillows um and saying that they are
diligent and Argent in exercise and that
um a neighboring King who wanted to
conquer them would not gain any access
to them precisely because they did not
have the soft and tender hands and were
vulnerable in that sense and then he
said the same thing about monks saying
when monks uh indulge in com for you
know having comfortable pillows made out
of down and things like this then the
mar the evil one will gain access to
them um so the so we should make a
distinction between the desire for
comfort and just technological
innovations taking place because that
can't be stopped right it we're not
saying go back to the Middle Ages so
there's no difficult with that outer
progress but it seems to me that um the
desire for comfort and the safety that
you mentioned the in essence that means
mentioned the in essence that means
basically that people don't really want
to feel
feeling that's what Comfort is or it
allows them to yeah not feel feel it it
allow it allows you to not feel feeling
which is present but as you have
discussed in quite a few talks already
the whole practice of Dharma takes place
on the level of craving which is always
in relation to feeling right so craving
to continue Pleasant feeling or craving
against unpleasant feeling but how can
one discern and practice the middle way
which takes place on that level if one
is living nowadays a life that is
dominated by the wish for comfort that
that allows you to basically hardly feel
anything that that that is going to be a problem
that that that is going to be a problem
not the fact that Healthcare might be
accessible or that you can get in the
car rather than walk somewhere um so but
you see this is hardly being talked
about so people might think oh I'm a
householder now I read discourses and I
see that householders become Noble
disciples uh therefore I'm going to read
the discourses and I can also become a
noble disciple but that is way and
continue living the same way yeah and
continue living living the same way so
that seems to me um a blind spot
uh that that people are
probably not sufficiently aware
of so this was kind of well this is
something you say often so kind of
ripping it from you but like the the
concept of um like these days I notice
like if I get sick say I like wake up in
the middle of the night with like a
splitting headache my immediate thought
is like I can I can just see myself like
taking safety and they like oh you know
I can just go to the hospital fix it
there's kind of that implicit assumption
that any problem can be solved in a
30-minute drive to the nearest hospital
that was absolutely not a thing in
Ancient India mhm those householders
you yeah something significantly less
scary than waking up with a heada like
the the slightest thing you get a cut
and it's infected that could be that
could be antibiotics yeah so the danger
was much more apparent M and so that's
one thing so you see it's a good thing
that people might now live longer lives
I don't think anyone here is against it
but if it comes down if it comes with
the complacency of all those things that
we just mentioned yeah that is then
going to become an issue then you
actually need to make double effort in
order to touch upon the basic
uncertainty that comes with having been
born in the first
place yes so if you're covering up the
fact that
feelings arise out of your control if
you if you if you have ample means to
deal with feelings when they arise you
will not be forced to find out that
actually the reason why those feelings
make you suffer is craving not the
feelings and um so there's that level as
well but it's not a coincidence also
that the practice of dhama in in itself
also becomes a way of trying to find
Comfort like not just
now not just the external comfort that
that's taken for granted as we said but
internally I also want to not even feel
things uhuh yes well well most practice
will be geared towards that like well
that's what we discussed like like an
internal SP or something yeah whereas
actually it is about uncovering the
liability to old age sickness death
because that no scientist has been able
to prevent that is and and they probably
will not be able to do that either so
when still subjected to that but you see
then people can very easily think like
yeah well that's in the future for one
thing right sickness and death I'm now
young I'm still healthy so I postpone
that into the future and even if that's
going to happen well uh let's just hope
that I have a comfortable death maybe a
shot of morphine if it becomes too
painful and then I die and that's it so
I don't suggest we now go into the whole
discussion of rebirth but there but but
there is that nihilism sitting there in
the background
when you assume this is the only life
you basically want to sit out the right
as comfortable as possible without then
realizing that against those
assumptions the dhama goes 180 degre the
other way so way so
um
the yeah so you want to basically be be
if you want to understand impermanence
which could also say is a form of
uncertainty then you need to
um stop covering it up basically so
because you can you can um actually
that's that's one slightly ironic thing
you know impermanence would be um along
those lines of your body being liable to
sickness you being liable to die at any
time the things that you're attached to
being liable to be taken away at any
time that's what impermanence is but
because we are so used to not thinking
about those things anymore like our our
existence is basically founded upon
ignoring those things so that we can be
at ease then when people try to think
about impermanence it totally doesn't
affect at all that level where that
Comfort is it's just externally you know
these sense objects are constantly
changing and my sights are popping in
and out of existence every second but uh
that that uncertainty of your being
where you're you're actual attachments
is are established that that's
completely taken for granted so it's all
um it all goes hand in hand almost like
you know the the way you externally live
your life and then not taking that not
questioning that and then approaching
the dhama with the same attitude so like
keeping it a distance yeah at AR
everything like at arms length mhm so
then like it's not enough now to have
all these uh external Comforts now I
want to have comfort on that on of the
wrong kind because obviously you could
say Liberation is a sort of comfort but
no like the wrong kind of comfort in the
sense of freeing myself from feelings
instead of freeing myself from craving
yeah so now people want to have even
that even on the level of their mind not
just on the external level MH and so the
like I said it's it's just a
continuation of the same same thing
and uh also another aspect that might
not be
necessarily thought about in terms of
um how those people were
living um you know there's a big
difference in for example if you read the
in for example if you read the
discourses and you see what situation
those people were in the ones who were
householders like Kata Pinda visaka
these famous
lay disciples that people would
sometimes quote as proof that you can be
you know living a household life and and
having children and still practicing the
dhama the part that they would forget is
that these people already had children
were already married when they
encountered the D It's not that they at
17 years old became so upon us and then
they chose to go the route of
sensuality so it's it's a it's a very
different uh situation because if you
already if you already have
children well they wouldn't just factually back
well they wouldn't just factually back
in those days if the the man of the
family abandons the the the wife and the
children there's a very like high
likelihood that they won't be able to
make it so um it was a very different
thing for somebody
to um it was a very dangerous thing for
for somebody to choose to ordain no
matter how much they wanted like in
ideally to do it um back in those days
than it is today because today we have
like healthc care you know social social
security I mean I'm not saying you
should abandon your children nowadays
just because of that but the point is
like clearly there is a there is a very
different situation in that sense and
they would have been staying with their
family with a very different reason for or with
with a very different reason for or with
with a very different
context than somebody might be doing
doing today yeah saying even the kind of
well one of the requirements for
ordaining as a biku is you need your
parents permission I mean in that
time like you had children to watch
after you when you were old yeah like
that was your kind of
survival token like that's what you had
to do to survive is have kids
so that I mean I'm not asserting to kind
of limit the Buddha's reasoning for that
to just this but like part of that was I
would imagine asking them permission to
kind of like compromise their survival
chances a little bit yes like that was a
huge ask yeah um so you can kind of use
that as an excuse today like oh my
parents but you know is it that same
situation yeah most likely not well they
have a Insurance yes yeah right yeah as
an American yeah and and so um that's so
that's the thing like if a
person has taken on the Buddhist
teaching which you could summarize as
saying that attachment is suffering
mhm and then they choose to accumulate
more attachments willfully mhm they haven't
attachments willfully mhm they haven't
actually uh acquiesced to the Buddhist
teaching mhm so it's not that these
people understood the D and then
proliferated theiry engagements it's
that they had they already had wory
engagements when they underst the dama
to a point where withdrawing themselves
from those engagements would have
resulted in Misfortune for other people
yeah so that's a very different
different situation and another thing as
well is that in ancient India
there were like well I'm not sure
exactly what the percentages were but
certainly love marriages were much more
rare uhhuh than they were today you
would be married because your parents
forced you to get married when you were
like even before you turned 20 sometimes
even as children sometimes they would
they would find the their future wife so
you would basically like find yourself
in that situation not like you met this
person and you fell in love with them
and you like for the sake of pure
sensual pleasure you decided to to um
build a life with them it's more like um
like it was either that or your parents
would disown you or something so you
find yourself in that situation and then
again that even though externally it
might look the same thing oh look he's
living with his wife I'm also living
with my wife yeah but the whole
relationship between husband and wife um
is conceivably quite different yeah so
people can ask like this this this might
be a hard question but you know just as
a thought experiment if you're in a
relationship with
someone if that relationship becomes
celibate for example just to go to the
heart of the matter you just as a
thought as a thought experiment is that
relationship going to stand or is your
partner basically going to pack his or
her stuff and say well if that's what
you're going to do I'm no longer
interested if that's the conclusion then
you should realize that that
relationship then whatever you tell
yourself that relationship has
sensuality as the as the guiding
principle because otherwise living a
living a celibate life would would not
result in that relationship breaking up
there would be other purposes for it
apart from this yeah such as you know
taking care of the children that you had
before or something
yeah yeah so because that's the thing um
the the
obstacles if you read the the sutas when
or the accounts of when uh these people
would get the right
view why they got The Right View there's
no mention of a meditation technique
that they did beforehand or some like it
wasn't they met the Buddha for the first
time they hadn't been practicing
Buddhism before that mhm and it wasn't
that they had to spend three months
building up their concentration skills
in order to be able to understand
whether he then told them what what um
made them understand the dhama was that
first he taught them about the benefits
of virtue the benefits of uh giving and
and making good good
Karm and then he taught them the
drawbacks of
sensuality of even the good results that
they would get out of doing these good
things and then when their minds were
free from hindrances mainly from
sensuality and established in that that
piece of renunciation
a then he taught them the four no truths
and then they understood on account of
that yes so the the factual thing that
that you have to recognize is if I
haven't understood the dhama having
having received like so much more instruction
received like so much more instruction
than those people did back then it can
only be because my mind is still to some
degree I don't know exactly how much but
to some degree it still sees sensuality
as
pleasant to the point where it's not
able to understand the dhama like it's
it's still
fundamentally because you can have all
the all the views theoretical views
about the for no chus or whatever but
fundamentally if your mind still values
sensuality your mind doesn't see craving
as the root of suffering cuz you nobody
wants to to suffer so if they still
value craving supposedly having
understood that craving is the root of
suffering you see that there's a
contradiction that they didn't actually
understand so that's what the the
so that's what the the
the that's why like all these precepts
and virtue and and withdrawal from
sensuality are prerequisites not because
in and of itself it is the dhama because
you can abandon all these things for
wrong reasons like members of other
sects would do even back in the Buddhist
day and other and in monastics and other
religions but it's
because that is the obstacle like when
the Buddha wanted to um became
enlightened and then he was hesitating
to teach the dhama his reasoning was the
entire world
is um clouded like their their vision is
clouded by Passion he didn't say he
didn't say you know they don't have
sufficient focusing concentration skills
it's their view is clouded by desire and
that's why he he he felt apprehensive to
and that was in back in the day in India
in a country which Prides itself on it
on its asceticism yeah like how how many
people were not like homeless
wonders I mean that might have they were
probably a bunch of them on the site of
self modification uh so that was the
obstacle but that's another difference
like now it's it's basically all the way
on the other it's very unlikely that
somebody will now fall into the like
aesthetic self modification the way it
was back in the Buddha's Day so a whole
bunch of people like wers would actually
also need not much instruction from the
Buddha in order to get it because they
were already living fairly aesthetic
lives yeah right whereas now it's the
other side of the spectrum so I would
I'm even inclined to say that even if
some somebody is not interested in
understanding the Buddhist teaching for
whatever reason still they would benefit
um from cutting down that desire for
Comfort because you you will just be so
much more uh capable of dealing with
change when unfortunate things are going
to hit you and they will sooner or later
um so again that that technological
progress is not the issue it it is
individuals seeking Comfort which is
rooted in not wanting to feel things and
you cannot fundamentally not feel things
so it's a tremendous cover up
yeah actually now that we brought up
this
um I had one s section ofes I wanted to
read out
um because you mentioned the self
mortification
thing here it
is so this was when the Buddha was
striving still not having achieved
Enlightenment so these are three simile
that occur to
him he said Suppose there was a green
sappy log and it was lying in water then
a man comes along with an upper fire
stick thinking to light a fire and
produce heat what do you think a by
drilling the stick against that green
sappy log lying in the water could they
light a fire produce heat no master Goa
why not because it's a green sappy log
and it's lying in the water that person
will eventually get weary and frustrated
in the same way there are Aesthetics and
brahmins who don't live with withdrawn
in body and mind from sensuality they
haven't internally given up and laay
desire affection infatuation thirst and
burning for sensuality regardless of
whether or not they feel violent painful
sharp severe acute feelings they are
incapable of knowledge and vision of
supreme Awakening this was the first
simile that occurred to me then a second
simile occurred to me suppose it was a
green sappy log and it was lying on dry
land far from the water then a man comes
along with a upper fire stick thinking
to light a fire and produce heat what do
you think agives by drilling the stick
against that green sappy log and dry dry
land far from water could they light a
fire and produce heat no master Goa why
not because it's still a green sappy log
despite despite the fact that it's lying
on dry land far from water that person
will eventually get weary and frustrated
in the same way there are Aesthetics and
brahmans who do live withdrawn in body
and mind from sensuality but they
haven't internally given up an el lay
desire affection infatuation thirst and
burning for sensuality regardless of
whether or not they feel violent painful
sharp severe acute feelings they are
incapable of knowledge and vision of
supreme Awakening this would the second
simile that occurred to me then if third
simil occurred to me suppose it was a
dried up withered log and it was lying
on dry land far from the water then the
man comes along tryes to light the fire
stick by drilling the the stick against
that dried up withered log and dry land
far from water could they light a fire
and produce heat Yes master Goa why is
that because it's a dried up withered
log and it's drying on dry land uh far
from water in the same way there are
Aesthetics and rahin who do live
withdrawn in body and mind from
sensuality and they have internally
given up an laay desire affection
infatuation thirst and burning for
sensuality regardless of whether or not
they feel violent painful sharp severe
acute feelings they are capable of
knowledge and vision of supreme
Awakening
so the the first scenario is
unfortunately what a lot of people would
be falling into like even by body mhm
they're not withdrawing from sensuality
so as we mention often the the precepts
like the foundational precepts that are
the very first stage of The Graduate
training on account of which all the
other things come like samadi and and
and all that they don't have even that
and then obviously if you're not
withdrawn in body there's no way that
internally you will have given up that
desire but so but the situation is even
worse than that you can become Monk and
and have uh be withdrawn from sensuality
bodily and mentally so it's like you're
not even mentally wishing for the things
that you abandoned uh you you basically
live almost fully focused on what you're
doing as a
monk but internally meaning the value
yes that fundamental value of sensuality
hasn't been given up so if something if
you were to get exposed to some um
sensually enticing situation
fundamentally your mind would still
regard that as pleasant you would still
be leaning towards it means internally
you haven't given up that uh craving for
for sensuality and unless you reach that
point it the Buddha is saying you won't
be able to give rise to knowledge and
vision and that is the um the point
where these people got when when the
Buddha was teaching them the dhama the
householders yeah like in that span of
time because obviously it was the Buddha
who was so skilled in teaching the dhma
specifically according to people's
dispositions that he was able to bring
them to a point where at that time not
only bodily verbally um mentally but
also on that internal level of their
value they had
completely in regard to past present and
future abandoned any interest in
sensuality they truly saw it as
dangerous and had no interest in and
then he taught them the dhama and then
they understood so it's like because the
problem would nowadays be so yes people
would recognize to some extent I can't
be thinking sensual thoughts and
engaging seuality and be meditating but
they would try to basically
compartmentalize the two so that you
know during their meditation there can
be no sensuality but on the outside
there can be and the problem with that
is you haven't in like you are again
withdrawn in body and mind from
sensuality but internally you still look
forward to these things like so in the
future at that moment you have a plan
that you know it doesn't even need to be
explicit it's just you still value this
so like if you were to receive a phone
call for some at at that moment while
you're meditating a phone call for some
super amazing opportunity for
sensuality you would you would be happy
so it is that fundamental value that
needs to be
abandoned and you
cannot uh do that if you for the future
still value cality so uh what I mean is
cality cannot be abandoned temporarily M
it has to be in that permanent sense mhm
anything like just just in a in a
mundane uh example as we mentioned
before like if you want to give up a
drug you can't give it up temporarily
nobody who who says I won't drink for
two weeks is actually going to be taken
seriously as someone who's trying to
give up their alcoholism that's right
yes so
um that's the the attitude that needs to
be taken like and only then are you
actually going to feel the weight of it
yeah right so basically then so to so
when people are considering precepts the
right attitude is for the rest of my
life I don't want to go in that
direction um and that might initially be
scary precisely because you now need to
consider the the whole of your life you
don't know how how long you will live
but right now you you're going to feel a
burden like never am I going to touch
this again but that's precisely the
whole Point um so if you don't have that
yeah then you have basically already
missed it yeah because that's where you
feel that's where you're forced to come
face to face with What feelings actually
are feelings get revealed when you have
no way to escape from them and that's
that's the that's the boundary that the
precepts create yeah that's a good point
when you are when you are properly
cornered things will become very clear
yeah you have no space to move forward
to move back to move left to move right
and that's when you will recognize no
the problem was
never even this pressure that I felt the
problem was my gratuitous resistance and
need to do something about it and that
will never become revealed for as long
as you still do the actions that
dissipate that pressure basically yeah
yeah yeah cuz for as long as you allow
yourself to do that you will maintain
the view that oh it's these things that
were the problem it's these feelings
that were the problem
and then the the the the issue extends
as far as as it says there you can
experience the cuz think about it like
why is the Buddha saying athetics and
brahans who would experience these
acute you know Pains of self
mortification why why do you think he
would talk about that in relation to
people who are not withdrawn from in
body and mind from
sensuality just kind of put the other
side of things into perspective no but
like practically why would someone be
seeking this self
modification well because there's
something else they don't want to
feel so the whole self modification is
in a way also based on not wanting to
feel something else yeah that that's in
a more sort of broad broader scope
but what what is it that
it like you're so you're trying to free
yourself from suffering right but you're
not willing to question the fact that you
willing to question the fact that you
need you're not willing to acknowledge
the fact that you need to give up
sensuality but you're doing self
modification yeah so that becomes a
cover up that sensuality is part of the
problem well exactly so basically what
I'm trying to say is it's a it's a way
of trying to overcompensate yeah exactly
that's what I'm so it's like and and and
you might think oh of course you know
this weird sort of random aesthetic
practices of sitting on a on a bed of
nails or something who who what kind of
crazy person would be doing that you
think about it many of the things that
people would do today are on that level
like you know do a 10 10day Meditation
Retreat where I have to sit down despite
pain in my knees for hours and like you
know endure that um heightened amount of
of displeasure to
overcompensate for the the fact that in
the broader context of your life you
don't want to give up sensuality exactly
yeah so it's the it's actually it's not
just back in the day it's the same
principle no matter it's the same like
you know these New Year kind of
resolutions people always like to do and
they last usually one or two months
after year because they feel guilty
about you know how they live life
through the whole year you know
indulging in this or that so they make
this resolution but yeah there is no
kind of that uh deep enough uh giving up
that why they fail and they feel again
guilty yeah so it's like a cycle of
overindulging overcompensating
overindulging over compensating and then
the guilt becomes a hindrance that is
just the mind being restless and
remorseful basically yeah so to cover up
yeah so that whole time that you would
be engaging in these self ification
practices AKA meditation techniques
um the the whole thing is is M like you
on a a superficial level you gave up the
the interest in sensuality but you're
still with that compulsion M of of
craving and whatever comes out of it
doesn't matter how good it feels when
kind of release it gives you it's still
going to be underlined by the same um by
the same craving so it's it's uh that's
why it's saying you actually have to go
in that direction of abandoning that
more fundamental stuff that you don't
want to question and then none of this
you will have to do like as it says
whether or not they feel excruciating
pain on account of self mortification
they are capable of knowledge and vision
because they actually abandon sensuality
bodily mentally and even any hopes for
the future any values for it in the
future so this like it's it's really on
the level of questioning like the point
of having a discussion about kind of
what the lay life is like as opposed to
the monks life it's not to like trick
people into ordaining or something it's
to like even if you don't become a monk
like the people who can be lay and
practice dhama are the people who are
like actively like seriously questioning
like the people in the sutas were not
like you take any of the Kings who were
Noble disciples they weren't not
questioning their they weren't pulling
their punches like you know I I'm the
Buddha said lay disciples only have to
do this much so I only do this much that
that's not how it works like anything
that you
justify that's going to be your obstacle
to to stream entry not to like arship
anything that you're Justified to
yourself knowing that it's craving is
evidence of the fact that you haven't
understood that craving is suffering
because you're torturing yourself
factually like supposedly you see that
this is suffering and you still hold on
to it you can't do that if you if if if
there's any real understanding of of
craving being suffering so um and and
the other thing related to what you just
said is that if you read all these sutas
about the the sutas that people really
like to focus on
like you know the impermanence and
meditation and janas and
foras is it ever address the lay
people yeah well so I have personally
went through it and it's counted
that like the only times where the
Buddha talked about these things to lay
disciples whereas when it was where they
were already sold upon us and there's
like five cases or something the entire
Canon there was also the one where s was
talking to Brahman on his deathbed and
he was in disciple as
well well not in that one cuz he was
this is the one where he was saying to
practice the Brahma of
baharas and this was the one where the
Buddha rebuked Sara after the fact for
not giving him kind of that next step
teaching well but it was clear that he
had gotten to the point where he would
have become an old this was a Brahman
who already practicing kind
of very renounced lifestyle yeah and
that's why the Buddha always talked
about athetics and brahin M which is
which is a different category than
householders that that those two
categories are clearly defined in the
sutas so what I'm saying is not
necessarily that the robe gives you
magical power no but that you will only
be able to partake in these things to
the extent that you try to live like a
monk not necessarily
doesn't mean that you need to give up
your children doesn't
need mean you need to give up your job
if you already have one it means
fundamentally well you keep the your
precepts and you don't accumulate more
of these things on purpose because that
clearly shows that you you don't have
your priorities straight if if if if the
if the dhama is what you're looking for
yeah and another thing we should clarify
is the difference between five and eight
precepts like that talks about five
precepts but that is just the minimum
ethical standard to not deteriorate as a
human being it is not like oh I keep the
five precepts therefore I'm in the
position to practice all the things that
the Buddha is teaching no no if you want
to make progress in dhama the minim the
bar has to be eight precepts or more
basically which includes again the
celibacy and cutting off the
distractions and and things like that
and because people might think oh
householder plus five precepts and then
I'm going to do Retreat and learn the
saatana yeah well right it doesn't work
like that yeah because like I said The
Bu or like the Buddha himself said what
is the obstacle it's passion the desire
for sensuality so eight precepts doesn't
automatically free you from no passion
for sensuality but you can be sure that
if you're engaging in the most sensal
acts of all you're not abandoning
passion so that's why it's like a
prerequisite for abandoning passion not
even that it's going to happen by itself
so
uh that those um like you said yeah so
eight precepts are the
the you could say eight precepts are the
basis for someone who wants to purify
their mind from sensual desire which is
the prerequisite for getting the right
view as all the sutas that talk about
they people getting the right view show
MH um so you don't have the Buddha now
and so you will need to bring yourself
to that point where they were yes where
their minds were dispassionate through
your own effort through your own um
relinquishment of things that you know
are necessary and cultivating those
values of renunciation to the point
where your mind actually
feels more at ease with giving things up
on that right level of you know your
attachments your possessions your
pleasures uh than with acquiring more
yeah and that can be said to be the true
prerequisite nowadays if you want to be
in a position to come and understand the
Buist teaching well even back then it
was yeah yeah no no no but but what
we're saying is like back in the day
some people already found them found
themselves in that situation they listen
to the discourse by the Buddha and they
get it nowadays that's it's much more
unlikely people can can read the the
Naya 10 times and still not get it so
what I hear you say is like people
should make an effort as a sort of
preliminary step to bring themselves to
that level of ethical consideration so
preliminary practices are not like
prostrations and visualizations and
repeating 108 syllable M ailon times no
it is fully on the level of Ethics if by
that we mean devaluing
sensuality because there's also maim
Manaya 24 I think where the Buddha
described in the most uh concise way the
sequence of purification
and purification of Mind was not the
first no it was the second purification
of virtue purification of Mind comes
later so people usually take it purification
so people usually take it purification
of Mind first then purification of views
and purification of virtue maybe next
life when I don't yeah you know or that
will follow naturally from those other
two steps basically or not even that
because you know people might think okay
like you know just uh I do what I can on
this life and then then in the next one
you know I I'll purify my virtue because
then they yeah that's already assuming
next life which is assuming more craving
and more suffering so so
um
the primary recognition that you should
have is you have such a a wide
familiarity with this dma and you still
don't have the right
view even though much less was required
for these people to get the right View
you that has to be because of this
prerequisite not having been met so you
can't assume that you are like no you
have to assume that if these people were
able to understand the dama without
having kept the eight precepts for 10
years and yet you're hearing more dhama
than them and you haven't understood
what you will have to uh bring your mind
to that level and it will happen through
this through keeping the precepts and and uh
through keeping the precepts and and uh
cultivating sensor trength because as
the Buddha said be not all beings are
are born equal so there there are
different faculties he said there are
some beings who are like um I think he
gave a SYM of like a like the Lotus
plants which some of them are like right
on the surface some of them are deep
very deep down so some people even
though they haven't you know because you
haven't found the Buddhist teaching why
would you be keeping the a precepts like
you you have know the natural tendency
of the world everyone around you is
doing this so you will do the same but
that doesn't mean that your mind is
fundamentally equally passionate still
passionate to some extent of course but
it doesn't mean that it's equally
passionate as everybody else and only
the Buddha or somebody equal to him
would be able to know that to you it
might seem oh look he's also doing the
same things as me yeah so Buddha could
see the distinction between somebody
just acting circumstantially in certain
ways but their background values were
quite different they were just sort of
socialized into a certain situation but
they were not like it it it didn't go
that deep the grp basically then the
Buddha comes up with some harsh similes
about the drawback of sensuality it
connects with that background value that
they might not have been aware of but
because it was there at one it at once
clicks yeah or or not even necessarily
having the background value of
renunciation but that the sensuality is
not as proliferated sure so it's just
like if if if the you know if a nail is
not as deeply buried taking it out is
not as hard so it's the same same um
same principle so if if you have been
hitting it hard for many years with with
this dama that that you been practicing
and you haven't got the right view is
because you don't have the starting
point that these people people had yeah
it's as simple as that and so yeah well
exactly so so
then uh so then we come back all the way
to to the beginning it is a fatal
mistake to assume that because you have
been born in these materially prosperous
times and with all sorts of
technological revolutions and things
like that going on that you are
therefore inwardly at the same position or even in
inwardly at the same position or even in
a better position than those people back
in the day were no it's not like that it
is fully on an on an individual level
and a dhama that is timeless cannot be
said right that that that whole
Narrative of progress should be given
into the right place it's on the level
of science outer technological progress
not the inner progress is on the level
of virtue that's an entirely different
domain so people need to start making
that distinction and then bring
themselves within the current situation
where there are these uh material
benefits on the level of The Virtue they
have to bring themselves to the right
point you could start to kind of
question thems what whether they have
this inner richness or maybe poverty
uhuh you know this in terms of uh virtue
these days we can we can say that we are
quite impoverished uhhuh sure so that's
good conservation actually yeah and it's
um it's
also the the mere fact that you're born
in these times already says something
about the Baseline of your mind because
as a Buddha said humans are
deteriorating um with time in terms of
their their natural values
so the fact that you were born that that
you are still here
basically that you're not somewhere else
means that you are kind of riding that
same train like if if you were in the
more exalted Nature by default you
wouldn't be here right now mhm most
likely yeah so being here is not the
best place in the universe let's let's
put it like that well it's yeah it's
good for uh realizing the D so this
human world is seems yeah but why
because there is that contemplation
where the the Buddha says that that to
be born as a as a human is is foremost
because but but why well compared to
Heavenly beings because that's more
comfortable it's more it's more refined
that's precisely why we are addressing
the issue now so so but now it is almost
as as if on the human plane it is going
towards the let's say daa realm in in
terms of the Comforts that that are that
are available to at least people living
in this part of the world and and that
is and that is outwardly comfortable but
um uh inwardly an obstacle yeah and so
if people want to get out of the whole
realm of existence they will have to
come to terms with that which is which
is obviously nothing to do with changing
anything on the level of society again
this is not rebeling against new
technological innovations no it is fully
inwardly on the on the level of The
Virtue yeah we're not endorsing what's
that called uh ludis LM yeah no but uh
so the but yeah it's important to
emphasize what type of comfort you have
to abandon fundamentally it's this
emotional dependence on Pleasure like
the things that are there are against
the precepts because like I said a
person can can choose to not question
these fundamental things where the real
uh
gratification and craving is being fed
like sexual intercourse entertainment
all these basic things they don't
question that but they start sleeping on
the floor not using heating not using an
air conditioner and that's not right or
just or just you know like going to the
gym and and really making physical
efforts yeah or taking cold showers
orever but then at the same time sitting
in the Post restaurant for big meal then
going to the cinema and then spending
the night with your friends and and
stuff like this so so yeah then in one
compartmentalized area you are actually
enduring physical discomfort in the gym
but but you then just just as a mundan
example but then you have to put that in
in a in a wider context so you you want
to start giving up those other things
somebody who keeps eight precepts would
would not spend two hours in the P
restaurants with with wine and candl
light and all the rest of it then go to
the cinema and start partying during the
night but now that is right so now we
live in times where where people sit in
an office for 40 50 hours a week in
order to spend one day like that so all
of that needs to basically go upside
down if you want to Now understand what
the Buddha was actually teaching yeah
but so so
um if you abandon that fundamental
comfort of gratifying what your senses
want um
if you actually well first and foremost
if you keep that as your value because
most of the most of the issues so it's
not that we're not saying like you know
ideally you should but if you can't well
you have to work from where you are uh
take up your precepts today like take up
the eight precepts
today uh it's understandably going to be
difficult but the problem is that people
don't keep that as a value like they
don't keep in mind
so all the janas and samadi and and all
the refined aspects of the Buddhist
teaching starts after this and so they
basically stay complacent with the
development of virtue that they have
which is like three and a half precepts
sometimes not even the five yeah
um and and uh and like you stay with
that and then you start emphasizing
completely other different things yeah
like so if you if you actually keep the
five precepts and even if it takes you
two years until you can or or 10 years
or whatever but you keep that as your
value that I have to be able to keep
eight precepts in order to practice dama
properly mhm that will actually like
that that's a much better um position
than than somebody who try to who just
does their best kind of here and there
with their precepts and then tries to go
into the completely like you know stuff
that Buddha was teaching to monks like
how do I practice anapati or something
which he called the abiding of the noble
ones and I want to be able to do it
without even you know keeping the virtue
properly so um and and so just taking
the five precepts like never drinking
mhm absolutely never on on intentionally
because even that for people nowadays is
a problem like you see Buddhists saying
well you know you the Buddha also said
you're not supposed to be too attached
to things and he said you have to give
up the clinging to rights and rituals so
that means you shouldn't hold on to
these rules too hard and you need to
understand that there's a middle way
yeah where as forgetting that the middle
way starts with fully keeping the 8% or
very not living as monks
therefore it's Justified yes so all of
that is already going to be problem
problematic you might not outwardly be a
monk but inwardly and the closer you are
to keeping those right values the better
your chances are for actually gaining
the right understanding yeah so I think
like one other like big difference like
in our days and in the Buddha time with
also like in our days now we have so
much access to information like with
internet books you can read read read
like listen listen listen so then it
become very easy to
kind of yeah kind of take like the the
gradual training like completely upside
down like contemplating like deep stuff
and going into the nikayas and all of
that just in order to basically justify
oneself to not make any actual effort in
the beginning like from the foundation
what need to be abandoned from the start
and I think one thing that would be
maybe nice to I think it's kind of
connected a little bit what's the
difference between like moderation and
the middle way because you kind of
mention like this kind of attitude of
like yeah I can drink a little bit so
that I can of let go and then I go back
to my kind of meditation technique and
stuff like that but has nothing to do
with the middle way yeah so the the
middle way is
basically nothing to do with how much
things you take like I I take uh half
the cake instead of the the full amount
or something like that middle way is in
regard to the things that are revealed
when you're fully restrained
so like when you never give in to any of
these desires like that are against the
precepts M and you start feeling that
pressure to give into them the middle
way is not denying that pressure
realizing that that is a bodily
phenomenon that has arisen on its own
and that for that very reason you won't
give into uhh not like it's not mine
therefore I can't give into it it's the
opposite actually because it's not mine
like as soon as I give into it I am
taking it as mine so the middle way
ironically is revealed by full restraint
not by moderate restraint so the but
that's also quite important because I
mean we don't need to get into that too
deeply now but cuz there's the other
option like you do take uh on faith the
full renunciation and full restraint but
then you go into seclusion and these
things start coming up and now you think
it's just about destroying them all and
not having anything and that's now the
the opposite of self modification so the
middle way is basically that's why it's
like the the whole gradual training is
forcing you basically to find that
middle way it's like give like I said
before it's giving you no space so that
you have no choice now but to actually
see the Escape while those pressures are
there pressure that are revealed by not
giving into them like you will cuz you
go into seclusion if you're not
distracting yourself as we've said many
times before with random activities you
will start having thoughts about the
things that your mind wants and there
you practice the middle way like we say
like we always say endure it without
acting out of it or or um the whole talk
we did on on the the origin of attention
and and enduring things on the right
level you see the arising of this
feeling is not the issue my craving to
act from it or against it that is the
issue that is the cause of suffering so
that's what that's where the middleway
is found and that's why ironically you
need to be fully restrained in order to
find the middle way not start with the
middle way in order to determine how
much you restrain yourself this would be
more more like on your terms so that
restrain your talking about is not on
your terms but on terms of dhama yeah
yeah so because you you you don't know
even but beforehand how much restraint
you need and you don't even know what
craving is so you need to take this on
faith you need to take on the fact that
the Buddha said okay these actions if
you do them they will always be rooted
in crav you haven't understood craving
yet but you take that on and if you if
you make a practice out of that like I
said you don't distract yourself with
something else and you keep in sight
that this is what is like that's why
they're called training rules actually
we call them precepts in English which
makes them sound like Commandments or
something but the PO word is training
rule so these things are the the
foundations for the training of the
higher virtue the higher mind and the
higher wisdom
so um with those training rules
basically you start to outline that uh
um where the work is like it creates the
table the the working table where you
will be able to practice all the more
subtle things that this that this would
just talk about so
um going back to the discussion of the
of the precepts so another thing that
the Buddha did advise lay people as well
in the sutas is
generosity so it was that was
essentially like the instruction on on
um to lay disciples with generally
revolve around five precepts and
generosity mhm and
so that's one of the aspects that are
that is quite quite often put aside at
least in Western forms of Buddhism
because it's like no I don't really care
about making Merit I want to develop
wisdom I want to become enlightened but
actually if you were to keep the five
precepts let's say you you you're not
going to keep the gate because it's too
difficult yet uh for now if if you
actually commit yourself to unwavering
adherence to the five precepts and then
you try to practice generosity not on
your own terms but like even when it
hurts even when like you don't just give
you know the the last penny in the that
remains in your bank account you
actually make a practice out of
relinquishing like when you see that
that this that your mind is reacting
negatively to this you actually use that
as a practice
that would take you much closer it
wouldn't necessarily be enough for the
Right View but it would take you much
closer to this um this passion and
relinquishment that is necessary to get
the right view then if you just keep
even the five precepts and then go on to
do a meditation technique yeah so that's
why I mean the Buddha wasn't teaching at
all meditation to lab people mhm to
householders mhm so it's um if if the
development has to come from that first
and then if you take if you manage to
upgrade to the a precepts then then you
can start thinking about Janna and
samadi and and all that stuff and and
another thing as well so it's there's
the five precepts but I think there's
another um formulation that they
sometimes give in special events where
you have the five precepts and the three
precepts on speech or four and then
livelihood something like that um so
it's basically um a further training in cuz
basically um a further training in cuz
again like it's usually sort of that the
the the problem is like you you
recognize okay I can't take on the eight
precepts yet it's too difficult but then
you justify all the other things that
lay people would do so careless speech
like talk about sensuality gossiping
um you know use talks about Kings
ministers uh politics Wars here and
there and and all these things you
justify to yourself because you're a lay
person but um actually if you can at
least do that that would also take you
much further in in in terms of
development than than anything else you
might do by disregarding your virtue and
uh taking these things that don't apply
to you Bally um
so and that's again the other thing
like if you really put Faith in the
Buddhist teaching and you have
understood that uh or or you have um
conviction in the fact that craving is
suffering you really need to be looking
now whether in your
life you're actually increasing your
Acquisitions like Acquisitions that that
you didn't have before cuz again like I
mentioned it's it's not that these l
people back in the Buddhist day they
they were you know totally free to to
ordained understood the Dharma and then
they chose to to to acquire uh a spouse
and children after having understood
that that freedom from freedom of
suffering but like today you would have
people uh who supposedly have faith in
the Buddhist teaching but again because
they put put the emphasis somewhere else
rather than this foundation of the
training then they would feel Justified
like I've been practicing for 10 years
I'm very familiar with the dama but like
I intentionally produced a
child so that's at odds with the
understanding cuz the thing is like you
have to recognize not we're not again
saying telling people what to do but you
have to recognize these are two
fundamentally opposite directions to the
extent that you can that you choose one
you cannot choose the other
so to the extent that you're still
actively seeking the other one mhm that
contradicts the supposed statement that
you make that you are really trying to
become enlightened like again it can be
understood if these things already
happened and then you you you uh take on
the Buddha teaching afterward like yeah
uh maybe don't abandon your 5-year-old
child if if if you put it depend on you
yeah exactly
but if if like you intentionally brought
about these these attachments and stuff
that goes against the fundamental
essence of the Buddhist teaching because
what what what did the Buddha say he
didn't the Buddha didn't say there are
two types of dhama one for late people
and one for monks he said uh in that Su
to gotami I think it's nikaya 853 he
said uh whatever you know leads to
dispassion mhm uh to Passion not to dis
passion to attachment not to Detachment
to accumulation not to diminution to U
Delight in company to Delight in company
not to seclusion to uh uh great desires
not Fess of desires to discontent not to
content uh to laziness not to effort uh
and I don't know if I'm missing one yeah
self-centeredness I think is wrong or I
don't think that actually comes up but
anyway so
we were put in the description yeah
basically anything that goes against
these things he says you should know
that is not the teaching that is not the
training that is not the Buddhist
instruction yeah so it's he didn't say
you know the D for people can sometimes
go hand in hand with passion and with
attachment there's another in where the
Buddha says I do not praise the wrong
dhama and the wrong discipline whether
it's for householders or for monastics
ra the right dhama and the right
discipline both for householders and
monastic meaning the same dhama and the
same discipline so it's basically just
to what extent you take it yes it's not
that it's a different thing no so um
yeah so then going back to the
generosity and The Virtue and the whole
gradual um teaching that the Buddha
would give also frequently to lay people
as you described earlier all of that is
going in a direction of giving up
suffering and so somebody by giving up
acquisition yeah so somebody might not
go all the way but people want to become
familiar with that direction where
suffering ceases um and we've just been
laying or rather describing uh what the
foundation of that is so because you you
can't do it the other way around it just
practically doesn't work like that yeah
so that I mean that's a problem people
would try to emphasize the anata the ana
the duka the The Emptiness and the
Magical insights about Consciousness
first and and then this other stuff is
kind of like disregarded or yeah or it's
Justified as well now it's secular time
so we don't need all those things but
that's totally good you with the
Assumption yeah so because again these
are these are train called training
rules for a reason so I mean sure you
can choose to go in that direction if
you want but at the very least you can't
say that you're practicing the Buddhist
teaching so that's a problem like people
put slap the name of Buddhism on it even
though they're blatantly contradiction
contradicting what what the Buddha said
so sure go and practice your your um
mystical insights or whatever but don't
call it Buddhism if you're not actually
following the the training that the
Buddha outlined and
um that's that's really the the
um the the thing that people should keep
in mind is not like um a moral command
of what they should do or what they
shouldn't do but keeping in mind that
that is the direction that the dharm
goes in complete abandonment of all
acquisitions and then you can choose to
take it partially and you will reap the
benefits of it only partially but what
is that gr what what would be that uh
partial taking up it wouldn't be partial
taking up of the meditation which is
like the that requires you to have
taking it up at least 90% let's say like
that that's a very tip of the iceberg
the the little bit of it that you could
get would be from this keeping of the
five precepts and generosity that's the
extent to which you would be able to
factually experience uh some amount of that um Joy
experience uh some amount of that um Joy
of giving
up and if you see oh this I would only
get even more of this in and in a much
more refined direction if I do start
keeping the a precepts and restrain my
senses and go in the further stages of
The Graduate training then you can um
take it further basically but you you
whatever you do you keep in mind that
that's the direction where the D and you
would do it based on having on a stot
that that's the direction yeah and
that's and that yeah so then you don't
cheat yourself that's the that's the the
real problem when you cheat yourself
into thinking that basically you got the
same product for 10% of the price like you go
product for 10% of the price like you go
to a store you you see two things they
look identical one of them cost 10 cents
the other ones cost
$200 do you like what anyone in the
right mind actually think that they're
the same thing obviously not and that's
what happens like the dhama that the you
need to pay the price basically yeah so
the the dhama the Buddha tght comes with
that price tag the other one might look
exactly the same but it's impossible for
it to be the same thing yeah although
that other one most of the time is
factually being charged for whereas the
real one is actually offered for free
but the price needs to be paid on
another level yeah of course so it's um
because it's it's that's why the Buddha
called it like you
know um in the future D will be
corrupted yeah but corrupt from within
yeah exactly it's not because some uh
some outside in Invasion but but because
uh a misrepresentation of the DH arises
and so from within the whole thing
deteriorates yeah yeah so then
um
the that that's really what what creates
the issue like back in the day you you
had different teachers and stuff and it
was clear okay these are the these are
this is everybody else and this is the
Buddha so if you were declaring yourself
as a follower of the Buddha it's because
actually you were a follower of the
Buddha but nowadays yeah many things
many different things go under the name
of Buddhism and if even without making
any statement about which one of them is
right or wrong if you look at look
carefully for a few moments you will see
there is internal contradictions that
are unresolvable so somebody has to be wrong
unresolvable so somebody has to be wrong
yeah and um well yeah like when you look
at a product that comes at a lower
price most of the time it's because it's
not actually the same it's not the real
deal yeah
yeah e